Edith C. Mulkey Papers WWII 156
State Archives of North Carolina
Edith C. Mulkey Papers
1942-1946, undated
WWII 156
0.35
The Edith C. Mulkey Papers is composed of correspondence from two U.S. servicemen and several people on the home front to Edith Carpenter of Demorest, Georgia, and Dunn, N.C., during World War II. It is unknown why Carpenter was living in Dunn part-time during WWII. The bulk of the collection is composed of correspondence from Carpenter's fiancé Raymond L. Mulkey of Demorest, Georgia, during his time serving in the U.S. Army Coast Artillery from 1942 to 1946. The bulk of the letters date from 1943 to 1944. After spending time stationed at Camp Davis, N.C., Mulkey served as a Lieutenant in the Pacific Theater in Battery H, 214th Coast Artillery Regiment (Anti-Aircraft), and Battery D, 950th Anti-Aircraft Artillery Battalion (Automatic Weapons) (SM). The majority of Mulkey's correspondence discusses the couple's relationship and future marriage plans, responses to letters from family and friends to Carpenter and Mulkey, discussion of Mulkey's living conditions in various unnamed military camps, and information on some of the officers with whom he was serving. Mulkey rarely discusses the actual war, and never discloses his posting locations overseas, though two of the APO numbers on his envelopes indicate he was in Guadalcanal and New Zealand at some point. The letters are an interesting look at a wartime couple's relationship issues brought on by the separation of military service. There are also letters to Carpenter from a male friend named John S. Bivens of Monroe, N.C., who appears to have met her while working in Dunn, N.C., around 1941 to 1942. His letters respond to the packages and letters he receives from her in 1943, mostly while he was stationed in the U.S. before shipping out to the European Theater in December 1943. There are also several letters from female friends to Carpenter.
Mulkey, Raymond L.
Bivens, John S.
Mulkey, Edith C.
The collection is arranged by creator of the materials, then in chronological order in folders.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by creator of the materials, then in chronological order in folders.
Restrictions on Access
There are no restrictions on accessing this collection.
Biographical Note
Edith C. Mulkey
Edith E. Carpenter (later Mulkey) was born on July 7, 1912, believed to be in Georgia to George and Naomi Craig Carpenter. By 1920, the Carpenter family was living in Demorest, Georgia, and George Carpenter and his wife both worked as cooks in a boarding house. Either the parents divorced or George Carpenter died in the 1920s, because by 1930 Naomi had remarried to Edwin Nix and the family continued to live in Demorest. Little is known about her life until the 1940s. Both Edith Carpenter and Raymond Mulkey grew up in Demorest-as Edith's stepfamily were related to Raymond's mother's family-and would stay in touch through World War II.
By 1942, Edith Carpenter had moved to the city of Dunn in Harnett County, N.C. She would become engaged to Raymond L. Mulkey while he was serving in the U.S. Army during World War II. He would apparently visit her while he was stationed at Camp Davis, N.C., in early 1943. The two wrote each other throughout the war to stay in touch, and apparently married sometime after the war. Carpenter moved back to Demorest by mid-May 1943.
The Mulkeys would end up living back in their home town of Demorest, Georgia; and in DeKalb County, Georgia. After Raymond Mulkey's death in 1958, Edith Mulkey and her son Raymond Jr. moved back to Dunn, N.C.
Edith C. Mulkey died on May 6, 2007, and was buried in Greenwood Cemetery in Dunn, N.C.
Raymond L. Mulkey
Raymond Lee Mulkey was born on September 10, 1911, in Georgia to Eugene Julius and Ethel Loraine Nix Mulkey. By 1920, the Mulkey family was living in Demorest, Georgia, and Eugene Mulkey was working as a bookkeeper at a broom factory. By 1930, Eugene Mulkey had become an accountant for a railroad in the city. Raymond Mulkey attended college for three years at an unknown school, and appears to have worked as a mechanic prior to his military service.
Raymond Mulkey enlisted in the U.S. Army before the United States' entrance into World War II. He was inducted into service on March 13, 1941, at the Reception Center at Fort McPherson in Atlanta, Georgia. Mulkey become engaged to Edith Carpenter while he was serving in the U.S. Army. She had moved to Dunn, N.C., around 1941 or 1942, and Mulkey apparently visited her while he was stationed at Camp Davis, N.C., in early 1943.
By early 1942, Mulkey was serving in a Medical Detachment at the station hospital at Fort McPherson. By January 1943, he was attending the Antiaircraft Artillery Officer Candidate School at Camp Davis, N.C., assigned as a Private First Class to the 14th Battery, 3rd Platoon. He would then be assigned in February 1943 to the 394th Battery (Antiaircraft Artillery). By the end of February, Mulkey had been promoted to the rank of Lieutenant after completing officer's school. By mid-March 1943, he was traveling west towards California, in preparation for being shipped out to the Pacific Theater. Between the end of April and first part of May 1943, Mulkey had shipped out to the Pacific.
By May 30, 1943, Raymond Mulkey was serving in Battery H, 214th Coast Artillery Regiment (Anti-Aircraft). He may have ended up at Guadalcanal at some point in 1943, particular by November 1943. Nothing is known about where his unit was stationed through 1943. By November 1943, Mulkey was assigned to Battery D, 950th Anti-Aircraft Artillery Battalion (Automatic Weapons) (SM). By December 1944, he was assigned toe Headquarters Company, 950th Anti-Aircraft Artillery Battalion (Automatic Weapons). At some point, he was stationed in the Philippines. By 1946, Mulkey was promoted to the rank of Captain. Mulkey was honorably discharged from the U.S. Army in February 1946.
Edith Carpenter and Raymond Mulkey would marry after WWII, and were living in Georgia. By the early 1950s, Raymond Mulkey was working as a engineer and highway project engineer for the Georgia State Highway Department. Raymond L. Mulkey died on October 26, 1958, in DeKalb County, Georgia, and was buried in Greenwood Cemetery in Dunn, N.C.
John S. Bivens
The "John S. Bivens" who wrote to Edith Carpenter during World War II appears to be John Spencer Bivens of Monroe, N.C. He was born on January 21, 1910, in Monroe, N.C., to Rufus Lonzo and Margaret McManus Bivens. By 1920, the Bivens family was living in Monroe, and Rufus Bivens worked as a farmer. John Bivens lived with his family on their farm through the 1930s. He may have attended and graduated from college, and worked as a teacher-but nothing concrete is known about this. By the time of his federal draft registration for World War II, John S. Bivens was working in Dunn, N.C., which is likely when he met Edith Carpenter.
John Bivens was inducted into military service for WWII in the U.S. Army on September 29, 1942, at Camp Croft, S.C. By January 1943, Bivens was serving as a Private in the U.S. Army Air Forces in the 358th Fighter Squadron, 355th Fighter Group, while they were stationed at Orlando Army Air Base in Orlando, Florida. By April 1943, his unit had moved to the Municipal Airport in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. By December 1943, he had shipped out to England for service in the European Theater. Nothing else is known about his life and service from this point through the end of WWII. John Bivens was honorably discharged from the U.S. Army Air Forces on November 20, 1945.
John S. Bivens died on February 26, 1980, in Monroe, N.C., and was buried in Lakeland Memorial Park in the same city.
Acquisition
Materials in this collection were received by the Military Collection at the State Archives of North Carolina from Douglas N. Rader of Raleigh, N.C., in December 2007. The donation was completed in February 2008.
Scope and Content
The collection is composed of correspondence from two U.S. servicemen and several people on the home front to Edith Carpenter of Demorest, Georgia, and Dunn, N.C., during World War II. It is unknown why Carpenter was living in Dunn part-time during WWII. The bulk of the collection is composed of correspondence from Carpenter's fiancé Raymond L. Mulkey of Demorest, Georgia, during his time serving in the U.S. Army Coast Artillery from 1942 to 1946. The bulk of the letters date from 1943 to 1944. After spending time stationed at Camp Davis, N.C., Mulkey served as a Lieutenant in the Pacific Theater in Battery H, 214th Coast Artillery Regiment (Anti-Aircraft), and Battery D, 950th Anti-Aircraft Artillery Battalion (Automatic Weapons) (SM).
The majority of Mulkey's correspondence discusses the couple's relationship and future marriage plans, responses to letters from family and friends to Carpenter and Mulkey, discussion of Mulkey's living conditions in various unnamed military camps, and information on some of the officers with whom he was serving. Mulkey rarely discusses the actual war, and never discloses his posting locations overseas, though two of the APO numbers on his envelopes indicate he was in Guadalcanal and New Zealand at some point. The letters are an interesting look at a wartime couple's relationship issues brought on by the separation of military service.
There are also letters to Carpenter from a male friend named John S. Bivens of Monroe, N.C., who appears to have met her while working in Dunn, N.C., around 1941 to 1942. His letters respond to the packages and letters he receives from her in 1943, mostly while he was stationed in the U.S. before shipping out to the European Theater in December 1943. There are also several letters from female friends to Carpenter.
- Raymond Mulkey Correspondence to Edith Carpenter, April 1942, January-February 1943; FOLDER 1; Mulkey, Raymond L. (Folder Raymond Mulkey Correspondence to Edith Carpenter)
- Raymond Mulkey Correspondence to Edith Carpenter, March 1943; FOLDER 2; Mulkey, Raymond L. (Folder Raymond Mulkey Correspondence to Edith Carpenter)
- Raymond Mulkey Correspondence to Edith Carpenter, April-June 1943; FOLDER 3; Mulkey, Raymond L. (Folder Raymond Mulkey Correspondence to Edith Carpenter)
- Raymond Mulkey Correspondence to Edith Carpenter, July-August 1943; FOLDER 4; Mulkey, Raymond L. (Folder Raymond Mulkey Correspondence to Edith Carpenter)
- Raymond Mulkey Correspondence to Edith Carpenter, September-October 1943; FOLDER 5; Mulkey, Raymond L. (Folder Raymond Mulkey Correspondence to Edith Carpenter)
- Raymond Mulkey Correspondence to Edith Carpenter, November 1943; FOLDER 6; Mulkey, Raymond L. (Folder Raymond Mulkey Correspondence to Edith Carpenter)
- Raymond Mulkey Correspondence to Edith Carpenter, December 1943; FOLDER 7; Mulkey, Raymond L. (Folder Raymond Mulkey Correspondence to Edith Carpenter)
- Raymond Mulkey Correspondence to Edith Carpenter, 1944; FOLDER 8; Mulkey, Raymond L. (Folder Raymond Mulkey Correspondence to Edith Carpenter)
- Raymond Mulkey Correspondence to Edith Carpenter, 1945-1946, undated; FOLDER 9; Mulkey, Raymond L. (Folder Raymond Mulkey Correspondence to Edith Carpenter)
- John S. Bivens Correspondence to Edith Carpenter, 1943; FOLDER 10; Mulkey, Raymond L. (Folder John S. Bivens Correspondence to Edith Carpenter)
- Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1943; FOLDER 11; Mulkey, Raymond L. (Folder Miscellaneous Correspondence)